<contents>
<description>
<p>The root directory of AROS contains this:</p>
</description>

<item>
    <file>_gdbinit</file>
    Init file for the GNU Debugger gdb.
</item>
<item>
    <file>aclocal.m4</file>
    Local macros for GNU autoconf.
</item>

<item>
    <dir>bin</dir>
    This directory contains all generated files under the name of
    your OS (eg. <filename>AROS/bin/linux/</filename>). This directory is
    called <shell>$(ARCHDIR)</shell>. Below this are two more directories:
    <shell>$(BINDIR)</shell> where the files should be put which the end user
    should see and <shell>$(GENDIR)</shell> where you can create a directory to
    put all files one part of AROS needs (eg. <filename>libs/</filename> or
    <filename>os/</filename>). The directory <shell>$(OSGENDIR)</shell> is below
    <shell>$(GENDIR)</shell> and all <filename>*.o</filename> files in this directory are
    collected to the <filename>AmigaOS.lib</filename>.
</item>

<item>
    <dir>compiler</dir>
    The C compiler for AROS. It contains include files, the source for
    amiga.lib and c.lib and the source for the compiler and all compiler
    specific utilities.
</item>

<item>
    <dir>config</dir>
    This directory contains the dirty stuff. Code which makes AROS
    live (mostly hacked up assembler code which you don't want to see).
    Anything is allowed inside this directory in order to make AROS
    work on as many hardwares as possible.
</item>

<item>
    <file>configure</file>
    This is a script which examines your system and creates a file
    named <filename>AROS/config/host.cfg</filename> which is used by the
    makefiles. Run <shell>autoconf</shell> if it doesn't exist.
</item>

<item>
    <file>configure.in</file>
    Source file. Run autoconf to convert this into a configure script.
</item>

<item>
    <dir>docs</dir>
    The source for the documentation.
</item>

<item>
    <file>license.html</file>
    Our copyright license
</item>

<item>
    <dir>local</dir>
    This directory and it's contents are ignored by AROS. You can
    put alpha stuff here if you want to avoid CVS complaining about
    it.
</item>

<item>
    <file>make.defaults</file>
    File with options for the make. If you want to change an option, create a
    file <filename>make.opts</filename> and put your changes there. The most
    simple method is just to copy <filename>make.defaults</filename> to
    <filename>make.opts</filename>.
</item>

<item>
    <file>make.defaults.in</file>
    This file is used by configure to create
    <filename>make.defaults</filename>.
</item>

<item>
    <file>mmake.config</file>
    Config file for MetaMake
</item>

<item>
    <file>mmake.config.in</file>
    This file is used by configure to create 
    <filename>mmake.config</filename>.
</item>

<item>
    <file>mmakefile</file>
    This is the magic file which holds the whole thing together.
    It has the following rules:

    <filtermakefile>$(TOP)/mmakefile,target</filtermakefile>
</item>

<item>
    <dir>rom</dir>Things which are internal parts of the OS.
</item>

<item>
    <dir>scripts</dir>Scripts which are used to generate code.
</item>

<item>
    <dir>test</dir>Testsuite for AROS.
</item>

<item>
    <dir>tools</dir>This contains build tools.
</item>

<item>
    <dir>workbench</dir>The disk-based part of AROS.
</item>

</contents>
