<chapter title="Background">

<section title="What is AROS ?">

<p>Some time back in the year 1993, the situation for the Amiga looked
somewhat worse than usual (doesn't it always?) and some Amiga fans got
together and argued about what should be done to increase the
acceptance of our beloved machine.  Immediately the main reason for the
missing success of the Amiga became clear: it was propagation  - or the
lack thereof.  The Amiga should get a more widespread basis to make it
more attractive for everyone to use and to develop for.  So plans were
made to reach this goal.  One of the plans was to fix all bugs of the
AmigaOS, another was to make it an OS of the 90s.  AOS was born.</p>

<p>But what is a bug?  And how should bugs be fixed?  What are the
features a so-called <i>modern</i> OS must have?  And how should
they be implemented into the AmigaOS?</p>

<p>Two years later, people were still arguing about this and not even one line
of code had been written (or at least no one had ever seen that code).
Discussions were still of the pattern "we must have ..." and someone
answered "read the old mails" or "this is impossible to do, because ..."
which was shortly followed by "you're wrong because ..." and so on.</p>

<p>In the winter of 1995, I (Aaron Digulla) was fed up with it and I posted an
RFC (request for comments) to the AOS mailing list in which I asked what the
minimal common ground might be.  Several options were given and the
conclusion was that almost everyone would like to see an OS which is
compatible to OS 3.1 (Kickstart 40.68) on which further discussions could
be based upon to see what is possible and what is not.</p>

<p>So the work began and AROS was born.</p>
</section>

<section title="What is the goal of AROS ?">

<p>AROS' goal is it to create an OS which</p>

<ul>
<li>is as compatible as possible to AmigaOS 3.1</li>

<li>can be ported to different kinds of CPUs, for example Intel x86,
PowerPC, Alpha, Sparc, HPPA and more.</li>

<li>should be binary compatible on Amiga and source compatible on any
other hardware</li>

<li>can run as a standalone version which boots directly from hard disk,
as an emulation which opens a window on an existing OS to develop software
and run Amiga and native applications at the same time and as a link
library which allows to create native applications with the comfort of the
AmigaOS</li>

</ul>

<p>To reach this goal, we use a number of techniques.  First of all, we make
heavy use of the Internet.  You can participate in our project even if you
can write only one single OS function.	The most current version of the
source is accessible 24 hours per day and patches can be merged into it at
any time.  A small database with open tasks prevents all developers from
doing something twice.</p>

</section>
<section title="Who does AROS ?">

<p>This is the current developer list.  Please note that the e-mail addresses
of all developers but the coordinator are missing.  The reason for this is
that we want to protect the developers from junk mail.	If you have
something to ask or say, contact the coordinator
<email>digulla@aros.org</email>.</p>

<insert>devlist</insert>
</section>

<section title="The future">

<p>These are things which are still to do:</p>

<ul>
<li>Use SDE - one binary which runs on any AROS hardware</li>
<li>Ports to PPC, HHPA, Sparc and Alpha</li>
</ul>
</section>
</chapter>
