<chapter title="Random Ideas">

<p>This part of the documentation for AROS contains random and unsorted and
possibly impossible improvements, ideas and other things which might
go into AROS V2.x, when compatibility with AmigaOS is still important but
where new things can be done.</p>

<idea title="All lists and public structures must be protected by semaphores"
by="Nils Henrik Lorentzen">
<p>A system like the hierarchical semaphores in pOS would be best.</p>
</idea>

<idea title="Recursive lddaemon"
by="Claus Herrmann and Iain Templeton">
<p>lddaemon should be able to load more than one library at a time thus
allowing to open a library which has to be loaded from disk which opens a
library in <code>libOpen()</code> which has also to be loaded from disk.</p>

<p>The daemon could also search actively for a library allowing the user to
specify one if it can't be found. Paths like <shell>PROGDIR:</shell> should be
searched automatically.</p>

<p>If the lib can't be found, DOS_OpenLibrary() must create a message port and
a message, put the port in the reply-to field of the message as well as the
name and min-version of the lib and then send the message to the lddaemon
and wait for the reply.</p>

<p>Open questions: Will this interfere with the way Exec handles libraries now
(eg. single threaded <code>libInit()</code>) ? Can this introduce deadlocks in the
locking of the exec library list ? What happens if <code>libClose()</code> calls
<code>libExpunge()</code> ?</p>

</idea>
<idea title="Extend on the datatypes concept"
by="Nils Henrik Lorentzen">
<p>Some datatypes-alike system where dataprocessing methods
can be added to datatype classes. (Eg. for pictures one could add methods
like <code>Rotate()</code>, <code>Flip()</code> and other typical image processing operators.
Similarly one can add sound fx methods for sound data). For this to be
usefull one should probably be able to add methods to a class one by one
(so BOOPSI can probably not be used for this).</p>

<p>The objects should contain the data in a raw format so that the methods
can easily operate on it. One should be able to stream data in and out
of the objects. One could have separate "converter objects" that
can convert from a data format (eg. GIF-&gt;internal raw image format
and back eg. raw-&gt;GIF.) So when you want to put a GIF file into
an image object the system will automatically search for installed
gif-&gt;internal raw converters and convert the GIF into a stream of
raw image data passed to the image object.</p>

<p>These data objects should of course have methods like <code>Show()</code>
and <code>Edit()</code>. <code>Edit()</code> could invoke your favourite
texteditor/paintprogram/drawprogram/etc depending on the
object type. (text/image/structured drawing).</p>

<p>Now, should these objects be able to show themselves,
like the old datatypes ? Well, IMO they should not be bound to
a single operating system/GUI system, but they could maybe show
themselves through some RTG system (?).
But the viewer could also stream out the data from
the object to show. When the object's data has changed, the
viewer could be notified and where in the stream the "damaged" data is.
(If a text viewer GUI views the first 100 lines of a 100000 line
text data object, and the last 100 lines are changed, it wouldn't
need to rerender).</p>

<p>As mentioned earlier one should be able to use this system
on different OSes, and it should maybe also be possible to
invoke methods on them over a network or even move the objects
in a network (using CORBA ?). This way a heavy operation on
the data object can be done on a faster machine while you are
controlling it from a slower machine.</p>

<p>By keeping functionality into small components, 3rd party
programmers can easily write freeware additional functionality.
(One can add methods operating on the data one at a time.)
It will provide very much reuse of code. (Just look around on
Aminet: There are whole bunch of different image processing
programs that implement the same functionality. This
should really only have to be written once).
If the system can work on other platforms too, we get even
more developers that can support it.</p>

<p>I believe that if some system should have any chance at all
of taking some market share from M$ it	a) has to be free.
b) must be available on as many platforms as possible. c) must consist
of tiny components that can be added at run-time.=&gt;This way it'll be
easier for developers to support it.</p>

</idea>
<idea title="HIDD Installation"
by="Aaron Digulla">
<p>When a new HIDD is installed, it should appear in the list of
available HIDDs automatically (eg. by file notification on the directory).</p>

</idea>
<idea title="Source code converter"
by="Aaron Digulla">
<p>We need an automatic converter for the incompatible features of AROS
to convert the old AmigaOS code to AROS (which can then be compiled on
AmigaOS by our compatibility lib).</p>

<comment by="Henning Kiel">
<p>The original Amiga Includes used to have an intuition/iobsolete.h
AROS wants to get rid of obsolete stuff, and therefore we are not going
to include iobsolete.h in our distribution. However, we are intersted in
getting software for AROS and this may be old, but useful.
So we need a way to support old sources, but in such a way, that the old
code will be converted. (Maybe in multiple passes)
This conversion-tool should do: (open, unordered list)</p>

<ul>
<li>convert old defines to new ones</li>
<li>convert old storage types (e.g. SHORT to WORD)</li>
</ul>
</comment>

</idea>
<idea title="select() for AmigaOS file handles"
by="Bernhard Fastenrath">
<p>I wanted to have a select() for AmigaOS filedescriptors some time ago, that's
why I wrote the AbortPkt() patch which sends an ACTION_ABORT.</p>

<p>A select/asyncio handler (AsyncIO.hidd ?) which handles allocation of buffers
and IO on multiple handlers could allocate buffers, do multiple reads on behalf
of a process and signal the process when input is available. The same would
happen for write operations (writing would block when the select handler has
queued a maximum of bytes or buffers for a single process).</p>

<p>A process that wants to exit could just close the select handler and leave it
to the handler to deallocate the buffers when they are returned one day ...
Under AROS the handler would be able to use AbortPkt() and under AmigaOS it
would be able to use it if the patch is installed and the underlying handler
accepts the packet type ACTION_ABORT.</p>

<p>The idea reminds me a bit of Unix STREAMS or NT device drivers: both pass
packets through several layers of device abstractions. UnixIO could be one
layer below the select handler and would translate it to a real select()
because the buffer mechanism of the select handler is part of the Unix kernel
anyway; so a write would block when the kernel buffers are full, as usual.</p>

</idea>
<idea title="Cache memory"
by="Aaron Digulla">
<p>I'm thinking about something called "cache memory". It should use all free
memory to store "nice to have" data like for read ahead or write through
caches for disks and harddisk or a printer spooler.</p>

<p>This memory is allocated by special functions. It doesn't appear in the
"memory used" list but is added to the amount of free memory. Besides
allocation and freeing there are two special cases. The simple one is that
some other application needs the RAM, so parts of the cache have to be
purged. The other one is to avoid memory fragmentation. It's not possible
or useful to use all the free memory for caching. So the cache should
always be one large block divided up in several smaller chunks. If an
application needs memory, parts of the cache have to be freed *or* they
have to be copied in unused chunks (eg. it's still faster to copy 512 bytes
than to read them back from HD or a printer spooler should not throw the
spooled data away).</p>

</idea>
<idea title="Double Buffer windows"
by="Paulo F. Zemek">
<p>The Amiga
has the Smart refreshed windows that uses an own bitmap and the Simple, that
need to be refreshed because it uses the screen bitmap. I want a Double
Buffered one. A simple refresh window where you allocate a bitmap and a
rastport for it, and this will be send to window on Refresh (or in window's
BackFill Hook) and when the Draw of All Buttons are finished, so you don't
get "flickering" (I don't know the correct word) on the graphic, and uses
almost the same memory of a Smart one.</p>

</idea>
<idea title="Child/sub windows"
by="Paulo F. Zemek">
<p>The amiga needs a function for opening windows into other windows like on
windows. The "Requester" does this, but stops the functionality of the
window, and doesn't have all Attributes of a real window. This or something
like this is needed for buttons which are over others, so the graphic of the
"bottom" one will not pass over the front one. And can be created new
functions for opening Windows/Screens, so you can convert a window into a
screen, create Public Windows and open other windows on it...</p>

<comment by="Aaron Digulla">
<p>This is dangerous; it uses a lot of memory, adds many
IDCMP event loops and the same effect can be achieved when using
clip regions; all we have to do is to make the gadgets public, which render a
window, plus maybe a BOOPSI subwindow class which installs a clip region
in another window.</p>
</comment>

<comment by="Bernardo Innocenti">

<p>I would like to extend Layers and Intuition to support child layers.</p>

<p>Basically, since V37 and upto V40 Intuition has undergone
a major philosophical rearrangement. The old structure-centric way of doing
things has been replaced by an object-centric fashon round the concept of
boopsi classes. Gadgets and images have been hit first by this new technology.
Windows, menus and screens would have had to, but for some reason it did not
happen (lack of time or compatibility issues).</p>

<p>If windows were boopsi classes, you could override their default behaviour
simply by subclassing them.</p>

<p>Some months ago I had a very interesting technical discussion around this
topic with Massimo Tantignone, author of VisualPrefs. We talked about a
possible design to implement child layers in a semi-compatible fashon,
which would allow nested windows as well. The current Intuition already has
some features (implemented in a non-OOP fashon) which simulate nested layers.
These are GimmeZeroZero windows and requesters. Screens could be considered
containers for windows, thus adding another level, but hierarchy stops here.
There are ugly design asymmetries that prevent you from drawing in a
Requester the same way you draw in a window and other similar problems.</p>

<p>I must admit that in this field Windows has a cleaner design (please don't
kill me). A window is just a rectangular clip region and everything from
menus to buttons is represented by a window. Dialogs and frame windows are
just two special kinds of windows that are attached to standard window
borders and system gadgets.</p>

<p>X11 has a very flexible concept for window borders. Insead of belonging
to the application, the borders are drawn and refreshed by the window manager,
which can even replaced at run-time.</p>

</comment>
<comment by="Georg Steger">

<p>Child windows could be done similiar to MUI's virtual groups = with
InstallClipRegion.  Unfortunately InstallClipRegion in AmigaOS can be very slow
and in case of SMART REFRESH windows also eat terrible lots of memory (hidden
areas in the worst case might be backuped three times!!) because it is
optimized for:</p>

<p>one installclipregion --&gt; many render functions --&gt; one installclipregion</p>

<p>instead of:</p>

<p>many installclipregion with few render functions inbetween.</p>

<p>It's also bad that there is no additional rastport-based clipping. Actually
the gfx-functions don't know anything about a clip-region (or beginupdate state),
they just clip to the cliprect list in layer-&gt;ClipRect.
For AmigaOS maybe it would be easier to not add real child layers, but only
child windows, which layers.library does not know about. I would also limit
the child windows to SIMPLE REFRESH (and maybe SUPERREFRESH) type, as
SMART REFRESH child windows would probably be too slow, and SMART REFRESH
layers are the most complicated ones anyway.</p>

<p>One would need special funcs for GetMsg/ReplyMsg on win-&gt;UserPort similiar to
GT_GetIMsg and GT_ReplyIMsg from gadtools.library. This funcs would filter
certain messages, for example divert IDCMP_MOUSEBUTTON to the correct child
window or "add" additional IDCMP_REFRESHWINDOW messages for example because
of damage resulted from a MoveChildWindow which would first add this message
to a private ChildWindow port. A ??_GetMsg(realwindow-&gt;UserPort) would
therefore also return messages from private ChildWindow ports.</p>

<p>For rendering into a child-window (assuming non-SMART child windows only)
I would use something like this:</p>

<code>
ObtainChildWindowRastPort(childwindow)
{
  LockLayer(realwindow->Layer);
  save realwindow->Layer->ClipRect somewhere
  create a realwindow->Layer->ClipRect list based on:
  
     childwindow->visibleRegion AND    visibleregion must be calculated here *
     childwindow->clipRegion           from a InstallChildWindowClipRegion() *
}
ReleaseChildWindowRastPort(childwindow)
{
  restore realwindow->Layer->ClipRect
  UnLockLayer(realwindow->Layer);
}
BeginChildWindowRefresh(childwindow)
{
  LockLayer(realwindow->Layer);
  save realwindow->Layer->ClipRect somewhere
  create a realwindow->Layer->ClipRect list based on:
  
     childwindow->visibleRegion AND  visibleregion must be calculated here *
     childwindow->clipRegion AND
     childwindow->damageRegion
}
EndChildWindowRefresh(childwindow, done)
{
  if (done) childwindow->damageRegion = EMPTY
  restore realwindow->Layer->ClipRect
  UnLockLayer(realwindow->Layer);
}
</code>

<p>Creating Layer-&gt;ClipRect lists for non-SMART REFRESH child windows is easy
as you never have to backup hidden areas, so it is basically an AllocMem
and setting some coordinates.</p>

<p>But if you want child layers for the actual AmigaOS, then you can only replace
layers.library completely, but not Intuition for which you need special functions
for MoveChildWindow, SizeChildWindow, ... which know about the child layers.
It is not a good idea to patch the normal MoveWindow, SizeWindow, ... because
child layers really need special functions like HideChildWindow, MakeChildWindowVisible.</p>

</comment>

<comment by="Bernardo Innocenti">

<p>This would make child layers very different from normal layers. You woudn't be
able to render inside them using exactly the same code, which is bad because
authors of boopsi gadgets would have to take special precautions to support
child layers. The same is true for requesters: have you ever tried to add
boopsi classes to requesters? Well, you would find out that most of them won't
work because of bugs in both Intuition, the gadgetclass and the subclasses.</p>

<p>I meant REALLY implemeninting child layers and child windows, not just faking
them with some clever patch. Each child window would just get its own Layer
structure and  layers.library would have to be improved to take children into
account when depth arranging or moving their parents.</p>

<p>I was thinking about something like this:</p>

<code>
struct Layer
{
    struct Layer front, *back;
    [...]
    struct Layer parent, *children;
};
</code>

<p>Where "parent" points to the parent (NULL if it's a top-level layer),
and "children" points to the frontmost child layer (NULL if there are none).
Children are chained together with front/back pointers in the same fashon
of normal layers.</p>

<p>This way you wouldn't need to install any additional clip regions before
rendering. That's exactly like window requesters: they are just a limited
special case of child layers. The main weak points of the requesters design
is that you can't nest a requester into another requester, and you must use
a different set of functions to manage them. Furthermore, you can't move
or depth-arrange requesters. If these limitations could be removed by
implementing child-layers in a simmetrical OOP fashon, you would just use
Open/Close/Move/SizeWindow() on them.</p>

<p>Another important improvement that could be done quite easily is turning
Layer and Window structures into white-box instances of boopsi objects,
like it has been done for Gadget and Image structures. Then the old-style
functions (Open/Close/Move/Size/Window()) would just build the appropriate
boopsi message and invoke the dispatcher. The same technique has been used
to add boopsi support in pre-V36 functions such as ActivateGadget() and
DrawImage().</p>

<p>Of course these ideas would require mayor reworking in both layers and
Intuition, but I bet it could be done without breaking the current API
and OS structures, so that unaware applications would continue to work
as usual.</p>

<p>We wanted to submit our draft proposal to the AmigaOS developers for comment.
If we could convince them of taking this way for the next Kickstart release,
we would have no reason for patching or replacing layers.library at all.</p>

</comment>

<comment by="Georg Steger">

<p>Requesters aren't child windows/layers in any way.
For layers.library there is no difference between a requester layer and
a window layer. It's just Intuition, which when moving or depth-arranging
a window, additionally to the window layer also moves/depth arranges
the requester layers of a window. If you tried to directly call MoveLayer
(I know, it's not allowed) on a requester Layer you would see that you
can easily move it out of the (not so) parent Window's layer or depth arrange
it behind the parent Window's layer.</p>

<p>The only thing layers.library would have to do in such a case is add/remove
damage to the child windows (whose coords are relative to parent window) that
are non-hidden, right? Or do you think child layer cliprects should be re-
"calculated" immediately as well, like what is happening with the normal layers.
With the ObtainChildRastPort, ReleaseChildRastPort I was talking about this
would not be done (= faster moving of top level layers) but instead ObtainChild-
RastPort would take care about it = you have precalculated cliprects (= fast
gfx functions) until you call ReleaseChildRastPort.</p>

<p>It is not a good idea to patch the normal MoveWindow, SizeWindow, ... because
child layers really need special functions like HideChildWindow,
MakeChildWindowVisible.</p>

</comment>

<comment by="Bernardo Innocenti">

<p>We don't really need any special code for child layers: top-level layers
would just be a special case of child layers whose parent is the screen
layer_info. This asymmetry is bad, but you can't do anything about it
because layer_info must be ratained for backwards compatibility.</p>

<p>Instead of adding adding a new set of functions to layers.library, we
would have rather implemented it through boopsi classes. Layers could
be turned into white-box boopsi objects (i.e: have a pointer to the
class at a negative offset from the Layers structure and optionally
additional instance data after the old-style structure). Then most of
the current layers.library code would be moved inside the dispatcher
of this new "layerclass", and the old functions would become stubs for
call the respective methods. I think that would be a clean and
extensible design for OOP layers.</p>

<p>Optionally they would have to clip the children to appear "inside" the
parent when they are partially outside the edges of their parent. Look at
Microsoft's MDI interface: if you open Word and move a document window outside
Word's main window, it gets clipped inside it.</p>

<p>Perhaps we could get the same effect of child layers without touching the
layers.library at all and doing OOP magic on Intuition windows instead.
What if the Window structure had a pointer to its parent window and a
linked list of children? Again, Intuition's Move/Size/OpenWindow() would
have to be extended to support child windows in a OOP fashon.</p>

</comment>
<comment by="Aaron Digulla">

<p>Moving this into Intuition looks most clean to me. Basically, what will happen
is that you get a window which moves with it's parent and where the code which
calculates the size of the window (or the cliprect for it) takes the size and
position of the parent window into account. That should work best and looks
simple enough to me to work.</p>

</comment>
<comment by="Bernardo Innocenti">

<p>On a second thought, there would be some hard-to-solve efficiency and aestetic
problems when child windows are implemented without the help of the
layers.library.</p>

<p>I think it can be explained better by showing a piece of pseudo-code:</p>

<code>
MoveWindow(struct Window *w, int x, int y)
{
    [...clip coordinates inside screen...]
     move window layer (relative to parent) *
    MoveLayer(w->WLayer, x + w->WParent->LeftEdge, y + w->WParent->TopEdge);
#ifdef INTUITION_CHILD_WINDOWS
    struct Window *child = w->WFirstChild;
    while(child)
    {
        MoveWindow(child, child->LeftEdge , child->TopEdge);
        child = child->NextWindow;
    }
#endif /* INTUITION_CHILD_WINDOWS */
    [...check for damage in ANY layer on the screen and send refresh
    notifications...]
}
</code>

<p>Here we recursively call MoveWindow() on each children to adjust their
relative position. Since MoveLayer() knows nothing about child windows,
the effect you will see on the screen is:</p>

<ul>

<li>the parent slides under its children, eventually damaging other windows
on the screen.</li>

<li>the children (which are layers in front of the parent) inflict damage to
their parent. These damage rectangles get immediately filled by the
layer backfilling hook.</li>

<li>each of the children moves to "follow" its parent, eventually damaging
each other (no matter which order you choose to move them). Again, the
damage in the children windows is backfilled.</li>

<li>If the children had their own children (nephews? ;-), you would see
them moving as described above.</li>

</ul>

<p>This scenario is awful and must be absolutely avoided. A clever workaround
could be adding a very complex function in layers.library such as MoveMultipleLayers(),
which takes a linked list of layers as an argument. I can't imagine what kind of
efforts this function should do to move all the layers at once in a way that
minimizes damage. For sure, it would be rather complex to write.</p>
</comment>

</idea>
<idea title="EnqueueTail"
by="Paulo F. Zemek">
<p>exec.library can have an EnqueueTail, and this
is easy to do, so the Enqueue already exists.</p>

</idea>
<idea title="Refresh only once"
by="Paulo F. Zemek">
<p>Intuition should not send more than one REFRESH message to a window (ie.
if there is already one in the queue, then it should be removed first).</p>

</idea>
<idea title="Clever OpenLibrary"
by="Denis Bucher">
<p><code>OpenLibrary()</code>, etc. should check for libraries in various places.
It should be possible to add paths for these and similar functions
and there should be a tool which checks and tells which library, etc.
would be opened (eg. the path is <shell>libs,PROGDIR:libs,libs:</shell> and there
is a <filename>x.library</filename> in <filename>libs</filename> and <filename>libs:</filename>. The tool
should tell which one
is opened and why (ie. <shell>loading libs:x.library over libs/x.library
because: libs:x.library has version 41.0 and libs/x.library has
39.20</shell>).</p>

</idea>
<idea title="Special write protection for libraries"
by="Aaron Digulla">
<p>It should be possible to protect some files (like libraries) so
that you need to call a specific OS/FS function to replace them.
This would allow to fix all problems with tools replacing libraries
with old versions. Maybe even a patch to <code>Open()</code> would be enough
which checks if someone tries to write in a specific directory
and calls a tool which checks if the write is ok. This is of course
a bit dangerous.</p>

</idea>
<idea title="Memory protection"
by="Dave Haynie">
<p>Stuff we spoke about over lunch, dating back to our days consulting for
Amiga Technologies. Andy mentioned the model they use for the 3DO
operating system (the original one, not the M2 version, which is
supposedly more like the BeOS).</p>

<p>In this system, each process has its own memory map, but the actual
mapping is still global (eg, there's just one memory space). Your
process can see the rest of the world as read-only. Functions like
AllocMem() transparently work from local memory pools attached to your
process, so things stay nicely page-aligned. This has the secondary
effect of making AllocMem() faster than it is today, since you only have
to involve Exec proper (locking the system up to keep things atomic)
every so often, not at every AllocMem().</p>

<p>I would make the extension to this that memory contexts become first-class
Exec objects. The System context would be the "root", with read/write
access as we have today. Device drivers that need the direct access to
hardware, or the performance of using references rather than copies, could
be started on this context. You could build alternate contexts, such as the
read-only underlay, as mentioned, or even fully private memory spaces, as
in UNIX. Obviously this is for new code, and Exec would need to add/enhance
functions for sending messages, copying, etc. between memory spaces. But
since you're not expecting any old code to run in a fully separate space,
some of today's bad habits wouldn't really be an issue.</p>

</idea>
<idea title="Installer as a library"
by="Sebastian Rittau">
<p>Maybe we could rewrite Installer as library, which
provides functions that are currently contained in Installers language.
This would allow programmers to easily write Installer scripts in their
prefered programming language, instead of learning Installer's own
language.</p>

<p>While doing this, we could also add methods to uninstall an installed
package.</p>

</idea>
<idea title="Installing AROS in PC BIOS"
by="Aaron Digulla">
<p>There should be a tool to create a kernel which can be
put into a Flash ROM or EEPROM or a boot file. The tool should be able to
fix all absolute addresses in the kernel, it should be able to create the
resident tags or a simple file system which allows the boot loader to
find, load and init all parts it needs.</p>

<p>The main reasons for this are: When you add a new driver (eg. a harddisk
controller), you don't want to have to install a C compiler just to be able
to boot from it. The ordinary user just wants to call a "install driver"
tool which does all the work without him worrying. Also to reduce similar
code, the boot loader will probably use the same code to load drivers
as will the OS. So the "file system" which is visible to the boot loader
must be similar to what the OS sees. This becomes more important if some
driver in the ROM is not loaded/inited during booting. Then the OS will
use its normal ways to search for the driver and at this time, the
driver must be visible by some file system-like means or the searching
for it will fail.</p>

</idea>
<idea title="Separate implementation and interface"
by="Aaron Digulla">
<p>An idea just stuck me which *might* safe us a lot of trouble.</p>

<p>We should separate the code from the interface. Code is here: The
code for the ROM libraries and interface is here the Exec shared
library interface.</p>

<p>As you might remember, I dream about AROS as native emulation (ie.
compile Amiga apps which run as native apps without arosshell).</p>

<p>Most of the problems we have right now (eg. in the mmakefiles)
come from the fact that we can't use the systems' own way to
work with shared objects but that we try to emulate Exec's way.</p>

<p>IMHO, it would be much better if we did this:</p>

<p>exec becomes a plain exec.lib which contains normal functions.
Then we create an interface for these normal functions and this
interface can be accessed as exec.library. All we have to do now
is to link the interface with the standard library. If we don't
need the interface (eg. because we have a cool autoinit feature
like the dynamic loader from Unix), we can omit it.</p>

<p>This way, we could separate the amiga-specific parts of AROS
much better from the portable parts. Also, it would be possible
to create different interfaces much better. And the interface
wouldn't be intermixed with the portable code as it is now.</p>

</idea>
<idea title="Configuration Database"
by="Aaron Digulla">
<p>Ok, since the topic has been brought up: Here is something which I'm
missing in the current config DBs/registries:</p>

<p>There should be a way to keep histories of configurations plus
"commit logs". Basically, the whole config should work with CVS.
That would make debugging much more simple (just throw anything
out and when it works again, do a diff to see what has changed).
It would also answer the question "why did I disable that" ?</p>

<p>And with tags, you can name stable states of the config and
switch between them.</p>

</idea>
<idea title="Better debug support"
by="Bernardo Innocenti">

<p>Debugging in AROS is becoming harder as we add new functionality and
the system becomes more complex. So we need more debug support in AROS.
Here are some misc ideas:</p>

<description>
<li><item>DEBUGGING MEMORY</item>
I'm thinking of adding some tortures into AllocMem(), FreeMem()
and possibly other system calls to encourage buggy code to crash. Mungwalls
around allocated blocks would be another great thing.
</li>

<li><item>ASSERTING EVERYWHERE</item>
To reach rock stability we must put all kinds of validity checks everywhere
in the code. Please everybody start using those ASSERT_#? macros and create
new ones for checking structures which may need further checks. I'm planning
a ASSERT_VALID_LIST() macro for checking Exec lists against dangling pointers,
infinite loops and succ &lt;-&gt; pred inconsistencies.
</li>

<li><item>IMPLEMENTING COMPLEX CHECKS</item>
Some of those macros might become too big to put them always inline. We may
need to add some support code into exec.library or perhaps arossupport.library.
Some I already feel the need for are _kassert() and _kbadpointer().
</li>

<li><item>DIAGNOSTIC DUMPS</item>
The need may arise to dump some system structures in a human-readable format
to help debugging. I've done some DUMP_#?() macros (such as DUMP_LAYER(l) to
track bugs in my own programs in the past, but I would like to turn them into
functions because they are usually too big for inlining.
</li>

<li><item>TRACING SUPPORT</item>
Assertions in functions such as AddNode() would be pretty useless without some
facility to trace back the call stack down to the caller. A single level might
not be sufficient and gdb can't be used to debug programs loaded by LoadSeg().
Unfortunately, this is a very CPU-dependent feature and I have no clue of how
it should be done.
</li>

<li><item>TRAPPING EXCEPTIONS</item>
We might benefit by implementing an handler to trap seg faults and other
exceptions. This could dump the CPU registers and trace into the stack.
Hits could be tracked down to the module responsable for them by adding
SegTracker-like functionality into LoadSeg().
</li>

<li><item>STACK TRACEBACK</item>
We need to provide a CPU-dependent support function to unroll the stack to help
tracking the origin of a bug. Seeing that AddNode() got an illegal node pointer
is no big help if you don't know where AddNode() has been called from.
</li>

</description>

</idea>
<idea title="Tool to show the number of missing/unimplemented functions"
by="Georg Steger">
<p>The idea is to have a software which scans a software for AmigaOS functions
and reports those which are not yet implemented.</p>

</idea>
<idea title="LibBase should become first argument of all functions"
by="Michael Schulz">
<p>I would like to put LibBase as first argument for every function
in every library (like in real classes). Then with __attribute__((regparm(1))) we
could force compiler to pass first argument (would be LibBase) through register
instead of stack.</p>
</idea>
<idea title="Use pipes instead of files to compile"
by="Georg Steger">
<p>Could we have some of this autogenerated files like "functable.c" and
"endtag.c" be generated and compiled on the fly by using pipes:
~generate this files to stdout and make gcc compile from stdin?
-&gt; no more functable.c and endtag.c files on disk -&gt; speedup!?
</p>

<comment by="Fabio Alemagna">
<p>gcc cant accept source files from stdin. It can do that only if the switch
-E is given too, that means only preprocesig is being done. In order to do
that you should call cc1 manually and handle all the rest (preprocessing,
switches to pass to cc1...) manually too...
</p>
</comment>
</idea>
<idea title="Native compiler for AROS"
by="Henrik Berglund">
<p>Maybe lcc would be the easies compiler to port to aros?
You can find lcc at 
<a href="http://www.cs.princeton.edu/software/lcc/">http://www.cs.princeton.edu/software/lcc/</a>.
</p>
</idea>

<idea title="Build Shared Thingy" by="Henning Kiel">

<p>AIM: The 'Build Shared Thingy' is intended to be a tool to generate
all sorts of shared binaries in a common way.  It should be only given a
directory and produce the shared bin out of it -- or at least generate
C-code which then only needs to be compiled.  It might read in some
*global* config file which contains info on the system
(OS/Hardware).</p>

<p>Mainly the tool is intended to make generation of libraries easier,
but it should be also possible to create HIDDs, etc. with this tool.</p>

<p>'How does shared library creation work?'</p>

<p>THINGS IT MUST DO: We must have an archive with all the functions
code and the specification of the interface (ie. return-value and
parameters like *.arch), so the tool can create the library-functions
itself.  There must be a way to substitute system/machine-dependant
functions like a dir-tree in AROS/machine/linux-i386/rom/dos for
linux-i386 specific functions which will replace std or will be added to
AROS/rom/dos.</p>

<p> We must provide a short description of the library (ie. Name,
LibBase, LibBaseType, Version, options like lib.conf). </p>

<p> The tool must provide standard init, open, close, expunge and null
functions, which can be overridden or better: you provide an abstract
description of what is to do (ie. library dependencies, initializing
code, etc. -- the tool then will create the code on its own).</p>

<p> Archtools functionality (inherited from the gawk scripts) must be
given: generate includes, merging archives, etc. </p>

<p> AutoDocs should be integrated, too, since they are closely connected
to the sources. </p>

<comment by="Iain Templeton">
<p>This is the text of the file
<filename>tools/buildshared/README</filename>, which I have removed and
put the content in this file. It turns out that some of this
functionality is implemented in the
<filename>tools/genskeleton</filename> directory, and some in the new
Python based archtools that Aaron Digulla has been workin on. </p>
</comment>
</idea>

<idea title="Virtual Desktops" by="Stefan Berger et al.">

<p> Enhance Intuition to support virtual desktops. This should be
easily possible with the (hyper)layers.library and the ability to
make layers and windows invisible. Windows by default are opened
on the currently active virtual desktop, which is identified
by a 32 bit identifier in the screen structure. If windows are to
be opened on a different desktop this can be specified with the WA_Desktop 
tag when the window is opened. WA_Sticky allows to make the window
sticky and it will appear on all desktops. 
Desktops could be identified by a bit, thus making 32 virtual desktops
available on a screen with the previously mentioned 32 bit identifier.
The sticky flag would therefore select the desktop identifier 0xffffffff.
The window and screen structures would have to be extended with a ULONG 
field.
Enhance Intuition with function DisplayDesktop(screen, desktopnum).
The technology is out in the public with the X window system, although
there is a patent on this afaik.
</p>
</idea>

</chapter>
